welcome to san francisco and welcome to build twenty fifteen and,
you know, welcome.
Welcome developers so,
of course you're all developers and you all have apps.
And, what do you want for your apps all you want more users?
And, as you heard this morning the best way to get more users
of billions of users is with universal apps for windows.
Some you already have apps...all of you probably already have apps either for
your desktop on one thirty-two or dot net on windows
...windows store windows eighty-one for windows phone or even
...and android.
But, for all of...get to...windows platform
we'll go through today kind of all the things that you need to know for your opt to be a good citizen
...behave properly...windows up.
So, my name is...henry
...a program manager on the windows developer ecosystem platform team and,
we're here today to talk about windows application lifecycle.
So, a couple became keeping things first be sure to rate all your sessions
you can remind based on the first slide if you want but you'll get another opportunity a little bit later to
rate them as wellat the end of the session
...to do this one now just kind of a you are here so this is the app model track for
windows a lot of you probably came before lunch from andrew session I hope you
waited that welcomes buying software tonight and I...to be a good mood but, we're here in this session at the
bottom which is the kernel how windows really...your app and how
interact with your app and how it sends you messages and kind of what we mean by that well?
By the events and the messages we send a windows
meetings like suspension and resume of your events...when
your application can execute the background how we give it accesses two-two
resources like memory and cpu so they can most efficiently use the battery on
battery-powered devices then of course just system triggers like timer events and,
events that happen within the system like push notifications and how those get
triggered into your app in the background?
And, of course the good news is that we've built this into the universal windows
platform so we build something that scales all away from our phone
...out he devices all the way up through tablets and desktops
...really powerful desktop and xbox machines in the surface hub and, the hollow...
And, the good news for you guys is that you get
to write the same code it runs absolutely everywhere but there are some differences with house
...behave obviously as we scale across these different devices that are different
amount of memory and different, different amounts of cpu so on.
So, before I get started here on the for application lifecycle quick show of hands how many
of you are...dot net desktop developers so a
lot like over half looks like...your windows,
windows store developers also half and,
windows phone developers so three halves
So,...you probably have apps for multiple platforms and of course that's why we're here is going to save you a whole bunch of
time to be able to build one app across,
across all the places that windows is and
...already building windows store applications or windows phone applications are not going
...much work for you to...already familiar with the basics of the application
lifecycle if you're coming from when thirty-two or dot net there's some more things that you
...have to learn in order to behave really well as universal windows up so we'll start off with the
foreman application life-cycle and with the basics of application lifetime
so your app can be really in one of three states not running,
running or suspended so now running is kind of obvious...not running users not using
...just sitting there on-disk if the user launches it
...current activation of...them, you know,
topping on a tile...apple come up...announcers the running state they're using your app
their pressing buttons are scrolling around...taping things...the...running and it's in the foreground.
A job...to the background
...this can be different things on different views but friends on the phone if they hit the start button and move to another
app that's considered your app moving backwards moving to the background the os will
then suspend your application so this point it's still sitting in memory but always threads always
...suspended so it's not running it's just sitting there completely suspended in the
...future goes back into your app...resuming event
...keep running again if at some point windows needs the memory that your app is
using for something also there's another app that's coming in for instance the user wants to use it needs that
memory will move your out back into the non running state so we'll take it out of memory.
You'll see...you get events as you transitions between all
...states and activated event a suspending events and resuming event.
And, but, you see there's no event between suspended and not running so when you move to
the suspended event you have to assume you may you may never come back out of that event you
make or not running so you have to completely serialized any state you have or
to be able to resume back into that event so this is kind of a little bit more states than the sort of a
...to...dot net what have which role you could think of it really think of them as having these lifetime
states but really they had not running and running didn't have this kind of suspended state in the middle.
And, of course for universal windows applications and all modern applications
apps are typically in that suspended state and, then and,
reside there's my we try...keep...there as much as possible because that's the kind
...efficient state for the battery and for the performance of the
machine what does this look like in terms of lifetime so this is kind of a
chart I have here that shows time...horizontally
...usage of memory and cpu vertically so when these are
...your app you start you load some data you consuming memory and then you have level
...the users is using your app and it's running
and at some point you get a suspended message of the hit the windows key if they minimize your
app so on that point we give you a small window of time to serialized all
your data into get into that suspended state so there you'll see whatever data or whatever data...the
...looking at any data...in the ui whatever you need to do to sort of build a
state you...reconstitute back into when you're...is resumed and,
of course?
Of course this point all your threads in your execution is completely suspended as well so,
after you finish that suspending state move into the
suspended suspending event move into the suspended state your app is not using any cpu
at all with exception of the background execution stuff that I'll talk about a little later but,
generally applications not using any cpu at all.
Course...can move back into the running stay we call as a resumed events you saw that
earlier on a diagram continue to run and then if at some point
in the suspended state and windows needs the memory for another
app the come in we will then move it to the not running states I think it's taken out of memory but,
you don't get the opportunity to run again between being suspended and, move into the not running
state.
So, I'll show you this very briefly encode here...move over to a very simple,
simple demo I have over here.
So, this is...see the alright so this is very simple project very
close to sort of the temple that you get if you did a new universal windows
application visual studio and I've hooked up here to the suspending and resuming events.
So, I have handlers for those down here and
we'll just walk through very quickly what happens when I watch this application?
So, here is launching the first
...launched event which is maps the activated event that I was talking about earlier.
And, this is sort of the first launch of the app government-run before so, we do, you know,
full startup from here and now it's sitting...running
...little chat application of written so,
what you'll see is, you know, while...the...actually none of the eventual fires
...just minimized there but it's actually running in the background so
...important thing to do when?
When you're testing these things in developing visual studios use this life-cycle events button?
And, you can see I can I can fi I can trigger the various states in
theapplication life-cycle state machines so I can...can ask the app to suspend
to resume or...move to shut down so that's moving to the suspended state and then to the not running
state so I'll show you what happens here when I had suspend
...suspend event fires and, what's going on here is I'm
saving all my local data so I have another method here that saved all my data to...storage.
And, you notice here this is an asynchronous method so it's important that I
grab the suspending operation referral what
...does is it says don't suspend the app intel I call complete on this...
If I hadn't done this what happen is the same local data would've built
a lambda and spun off on a different thread to save my data which is great because it doesn't because
...not on the ui thread it's happening in the background but
dui thread would finish and windows within think your apples and executing
...would move us into the spend state so I grab the referral here and,
that's that tells that tells windows to keep the app around intel
choices complete now you still get to run forever so when I call suspending here so I have a little
...that comes up ...opposite spending and, then I get
it depends a little bit between mobile in windows and are different skews what the with...
with typically it's around five seconds that you'll get to save all your data?
And, do whatever you need to do in the background so?
And, I'll just actually before I do more code I'll show you what happens when I do resume.
Citation so,
I get the resume event and then of course I read on my data back and here I'm showing...
That's resuming.
So, that's why I move...suspended in the resuming state.
And, using a using visual studio sort of force those events that happen.
Now what I'm going to do here is I'm going to now try and save some data
...to the klout which takes a little bit longer and,
I'm going to do this not in the debugged just to show you guys what happens so,...app here with...
And, as...comes up so the same app and other...minimized here so,
the apples now moving into the spending say now the break point and get hit one of the debug attached but,
what's happening you'll notice that...not coming up saying I'm suspended.
And, that's because my app a sitting in this saving cloud data state
is never actually entering the suspended state.
Eventually...you guys notice down here but the icon disappear so what happen we
can go to the logs here and we can see the top log here that windows
...my application hong was because I spent too long and that resuming method.
And, window and, windows made the call though they thought the
...taking too long and that we needed to terminated so that we could bring the next app
...that is the user needed of course we do this sort of keep performance really,
really good for universal windows applications.
So, the next outcome launch really quickly so we don't have too much
contention and app running in the background trying to shut down another app coming in.
But, what if we needed that extra time?
So, what we need that extra time to save data cloud you saw
...a particular case I mean I'm...reason we powerful laptop here there's not that much going on
in the machine there really is no reason why we can let the app run a little bit longer?
So, we've introduced...windows ten for universal
...is it's concept of extended execution and what this is
a laos your application to ask for more time to not be suspend?
...use the same diagrams before and,
we look at this...in the running stage.
And,...suspending event at this point
we can requests extended execution session.
I'll show you this encode in a second and,
what this does...windows is hey if there's resources available just let me keep running for a little bit longer?
And, of course if there are...available
...you do that so you'll stay in this case you'll stay in that suspending...and,
you can keep you can keep a saving data or uploading data or whatever you need to do and then
when you're done you want to the suspended state
...windows needs the resource for something else if the app that's coming in the next thing
...trying to do needs a lot of memory
run a memory constrain device or if you're taking a very long-time and the battery gets lower
...to a state where we need to...conserve it...message
at that point you need just you need to...very quickly only get a second clean-up?
So, I'll show you this here quickly encode.
So, this is the same the same app here.
And, I'm not my unsuspecting methods I'm going to take this code here.
And, I...replace it with this extended executions
...execution session so.
What...I done here so I have created a new extended execution
session right here and I've supplied a couple a couple parameters so
...said the reason is I'm saving data and,
you'll see in the...of the sdk there's only a few reasons location tracking which
...saving data...unspecified...will probable extend in the future
...the current build use of is only three options you have an you must
supplier reason and, as well as a description which are things that will show up in the
ui to tell the user what's going on the background if they need to figure out...why
...app still running or why things are going on the background so I into the...the reason
hook up to the revoke event which I mentioned earlier so hooked up here if that revoke
...called...close my connection really quickly and kinda get out of the way
then the first thing I do is I say my local data I know this doesn't take very much time so it's going to do that anyways I
know I can get that done in the time that windows gives me if I have my extent execution allow
...I can allowed back so I can potentially...or...denied if there's no resources available at
the start we won't even give you the session to begin with but typically,
typically you'll get...at this point I'll start saving my cloud data?
So, we can see...the same app here.
And, we can see continuing to run if I if I minimize here for
...call...operator...button.
All move through all this.
And, then I save my data and I check I check...result here is allowed.
And, now I...my data cloud.
So, take a few seconds because of my data take a long-time to the cloud maybe amount
of full connection or something like that it's just turning around...my data...the background and then I'll send a
...notification when we're done?
Unless I'm having a bug where it's not it'll show up in here...a second.
Yeah, so, maybe that doesn't come through anyway you have to trust me that tells would come through and,
you would you get...not of you'd your session complete and then you move into the suspending state.
So, that's...of one-half of extended execution.
The other option is to call
centre execution at some point while...app is running in the foreground not during the suspended method.
...suspended call back event of course this could be if,
you know, ahead of time that you're going to want to...running the background so, you
know, example using the reasons that we have that I showed you before is background
location tracking so-if you have a turn by turn navigation application...
a fitness application once attract the users location in the background whenever you start that session, you know,
when you click turn by turn start turn by turn our start your run
your bike ride or whatever it is for your app you can request your extension then
...and in that case your app won't even get the suspended event?
You can listen to the core window if you want to understand when your...the for
...not and you can listen to the memory manager events to tell you if the amount of memory your
...allowed to use changes if
your memory caps change but you won't get that suspended about you just keep running in the background
...if windows needs resource for something else will send you the revoked event and, your app
...clean-up and typically a question resend you revoked because we need to resources for something we're not just going to
enter the suspension in this case...a suspend and terminate.
So, I'll show you really...they actually have here kind of neat
the actual maps application this is the maps app that ships again
...a universal windows apps of the same app ships on windows,
windows phone all windows devices that has map that have maps.
...wi-fi little slow here.
It's like the maps and coming anyways so,
I can ask maps directions so, I can say well I want to go back to my hotel here so, give me
directions...me driving directions...switch over...going on.
All right so this is the real maps out here.
And, I think my connections a little slow so I'm not getting the
formats coming in has got the streets data looks like the traffic data which is probably all any
so, I've just asked to take me for my location to the to my hotel
and walking directions that...a little bit quicker and, then when I click go?
Here now the maps app has entered the.
Has entered
...its extended execution session and...exactly the same thing here except this is not actually in
a suspended event this is just one I've started be started
the navigation session the same thing I'm creating extend execution sessiongiving a look
a reason of location tracking checking the results and,
if it's allowed in start mynavigation session in this case here
they're subscribing to the events of core windows...they know often the foreground or not?
So, now also maps...now so now
...may term return directions of course I can minimize this and, it will still give me my directions.
So, those are kind of the two ways that you can use...execution.
And, of course as I mentioned this will very little bit
based on devices on how much memory they have to how much time you'll get is not guaranteed
...opportunistic thing on desktops with lots of memory you'll be able to run
pretty much on constrained in the background on some of the phone devices and io...devices where there's
very little memory...typically only enough memory to keep one or two apps active...the time you'll
find the amount of time that you can run in this state is often much shorter.
So, that's kind of the big new piece that we have for foreground execution windows telling
...move over now to background execution.
And, when I go back and execution
what I mean here is really just ways that your app can come alive in the background
are...user back in you know, either by responding to you know,
push notifications or events in the back system events in the background update their to
update your tile or things like tracking again tracking location using geo
fences or
...music in the background...connecting to bluetooth devices there's a really cases where
your opposite running but it's responding to things happening on the device and the system events?
And, backer execution in general is kind of had a long story on both windows,
windows phone...the good news is again here we've completely converge all.
All windows skews both desktop and windows phone and, all
...the all the windows ten ...so if so
...windows phone developers and kind of windows phone you may
remember background agents which are things that would fire periodically agents that would
fire every thirty minutes so you could update your tile and, then if you're coming from windows
age you're familiar with the concept of a background tasks
...triggers we at we added those in windows phone...
So, we had kind of a converge background model...windows eight between windows
...windows phone aone if you are building
...store applications as well as silverlight aone applications could also use the converge
...background...
...question windows ten everyone's big happy family all
the windows skews all use the same background execution model.
So, those are you coming from when thirty-two or dot net where you're not really
familiar with this concept of having a separate model for running in the background the way we define
background execution on windows of windows universal
popular universal windows platform is with triggers and background tasks so background
tasks kind of the unit the module that actually runs in the background code that runs the background
the triggers the thing that causes that module to start running that code start-one.
And, app subscribe to triggers and windows triggers fire code start running so,
for example, you can subscribe to...notification trigger your background tackle fire
...push notification comes in geo fencing as well if...if you're if
you're device moves locations it can cross a geo fence which will cause a which is
you get within a particular radius of.
Of some location and, you have a trigger find those cases obviously bluetooth as well
you know,...with bands and,
all sorts of devices watches and smart watches on we have to notifications by
a bluetooth and, your...subscribe to things like that heart rate monitors so on that
...booted devices regular timer events or system events just things happening
on the system periodic timers again wi-fi becoming available users logging in
that kind of stuff you can subscribe to of course apps services there's a whole session on
apps services and apt app communication I'm a little bit later in the week but those are also
...by background tasks...those are kind of interesting because that's a case where you can actually
your app can call another apps background service
background task to do to do work on your behalf so, it allows kind of this
web apps of apps to...other apps to get information on have worked on for them.
So, just an introduction I'll give a really quick demo here.
On the basics of background tasks.
And, a couple things that have changed as we converged
are background execution model across windows across all the windows skews.
So, this is my simple is again a very simple
...my same simple chat application what I've done here is when this page loads
...register much...tasks so the first thing that I
need to do is request access to run the...
...minimize this you guys can see it so,
I'm calling here the backer execution manager and kang request access.
And, what this does is it asks windows to give this
...permission to run a background your app has to do this if...to run
in the background of doesn't do this none of the triggers the...will fire?
If you're coming from windows the store development on windows
...windows aone.
Calling this api would bring up
some windows you-are-there...ask the user to pin there...
For universal windows apps we don't we don't do that so that's kind of an important distinction
...more similar to the windows phone model where your
apple just typically be granted access anyways cases where you would
...access...the user has explicitly just a larger out from running in the background so,
we have battery...across all windows all windows desktop and windows mobile now so
...could go into battery saver...the background task control panel and,
prevent your...from...in the background if they don't want your
...to be consuming battery...doing stuff in the background that would be case where you would get denied so
you should always request access there's also a get on here that you can call you ever want to check if the
users changed the state of whether you can run in the background.
Yeah, so, there's a get accessible...can call...
So, that's requesting around the background also,
you know, best practice is to unregistered any tasks that you have so I have a
...check...the timer task already registered and
on registered here some enumerating all the tasks.
Here and then registering them.
And, then finally I'm going to register my task here so in this case here
...a time a timer trigger.
...so create a timer trigger the parameters this takes it takes a
time-out of time interval fifteen minutes and then one shot means I want
to recur not so
things to false means I want the timer we occur every fifteen minutes create this thing called
the background task builder which helps me build these task instances given a name
and entry point so I've already added to the solution here a
...rt component that has my background task...so I'll show you...second but,
so, I specify that...my entry point my timer task here I said the trigger I can also set conditions.
So, I could for instance.
Conferences also add a condition to here and,
what conditions are conditions kind of work with triggers
as something else that must happen in order for that triggered a fire so?
I can add...system condition
...sorry year-ago system condition type of
say the internet available...that case this.
...new system condition.
Descriptive anyways you can add system condition...that will be something
though also have to be true for that task to fires in that case I can
...system condition and if the internet...available my time trigger wouldn't fire
...would happen is after the fifty-minute interval my timer would latch.
Which are manage ready to fire and then as soon as internet became available the trigger would fire my background task
would run?
So,...check here for the registration.
Here I can then get the name of so now register my task.
So, I can run this.
And, we can already wait around for fifteen minutes for this triggered a
...getting we're not going away for that to happen again, handy.
Visual studio will give us a in the life-cycle events...background tasks
...registration break point lifecycle events for background tasks we can are
...events menu we can see our list of
background tasks here so I can in this case explicitly fire the timer tasks and,
...point on there...hit the run method and, that just
popped the toast so do that again so we can look at the actual task here so,
I told you before this task was ...rt component that added
to the solution implements I background tasking kind of
the only interesting thing that I background task has this one method and the run
method is what gets called when you're...when your trigger fires.
you can see here when I force that task to fire a via visual studio
my run method is called a hooking up here to cancel method this is what windows
we'll call if you run out of time to run your background task so,
I can handle that down below that I showed...
And,...and such as showing a...down here in this code and,
then one more thing you have to do to finish registering your background task with two more things one is you
have to reference it from your foreground project.
But, then also you have to add
a entry in your manifest so here we see extensions,
extensions element being added is also a wizard for this in the designer that makes
...a fair bit simpler but this shows you exactly what's going on
...created a background task here specify the entry point to be
in my background task assembly in the timer task
costs.
...I've said that my tasks
...timer and here you can specify all sorts of different task types as well.
So, that's the basics of background tasks.
We have a bunch we have a bunch of triggers if you've been...from...a one we
had a system triggers time triggers...triggers those have been around for a while.
And, windows
phony one we added a bunch of new triggers cash file which is for grabbing,
grabbing data from the cloud for file pickers a
couple a couple bluetooth triggers device connection trigger gadsden rf
...or...bluetooth location trigger which is for geo fencing.
And, then a windows...more triggers so
we but you almost double the number of triggers that we have we've added a few triggers
for accessing the data store of appointments and contacts on
the device more bluetooth triggers for bluetooth or bluetooth
...as well as device watcher which is a new type of bluetooth figure that can listen,
listen foradvertisements from bluetooth devices activity
...to censored to do sensor triggers activity
...trigger and sensor data threshold trigger which can be used for things like parameters listening to the
...kind of stuff a couple triggers for toast notifications
so-if...if the user.
Taps on our works with your toast notification you actionable
toast notification or notifications...the action center those will fire trigger which can
activated background task and you can do some work and, then the application trigger and socket activity trigger I won't ruin
...surprise for the talk with those...second but all the ones above that
...sessions later on appointee...the dec where folks talk about those triggered.
So, those are all the new triggers that we've added in windows
ten we've also...course on all windows on
windows desktop and windows phone windows mobile as long as you know,
as long as obviously device supports those particular things
...the devices never gps than obviously location triggers locker fire so,
more good news we've converged resource management of background tasks across,
across windows across all windows devices.
If you remember if you're coming from windows aone there
was this concept of...cpu time and
...pool of cpu resources that your app would have a access to in the background of used
...those resources would have to wait for that cpu...refill.
...things a little bit here and, separated for default background tasks
...look very similar to the model again we had on windows phone for windows phony
one so, you have a memory cap and this is for...make devices here is this
scales up as we move up to more devices with more memory but, on...of
...five twelve make devices which are some are advice with the least amount of memory your background
task get sixteen megabytes of memory to run and, we'll run for thirty seconds something does
...thirty seconds in the background after twenty five seconds...running will send
the cancel notification to your to your
task so you will get some warning that your time is about to run out so,
you get twenty...plus five seconds to run and you get at least ten percent of cpu so that's
kind of a soft cap of there's nothing else going on in the device you can use you know, as much debuts available
but you're guaranteed to get that ten percent and of course task can be blocked...the users block them and battery
saver or in the background task control panel the other the others
sat is long-running or opportunistic background tasks those typically
have the same memory caps but they can run for as long as...resources available so not just for thirty
seconds to use me they can run much longer if there's resources available on
the device so the triggers that are that are opportunistic triggers...the application trigger
...talk about the second...trigger which is a trigger that fires when wi-fi is available
when the devices plugged in when it's in a good battery state?
Sorry not wi-fi...I was an old condition...
about the device used trigger which is used for connecting to devices in the background.
that's kind of resource management for background tasks sort of related to resource management...this
is kind of a complex feature what's important to talk about is that we've added the ability to host
background tasks in process with your foreground so what does
this mean well typically on the left here is how background task works
is hopefully it's host in the completely separate process from your application the application
be running in your background task can be running in two separate processes and, they never really talk to each
other lifetime is not intertwined anyway but,...you can do now and windows ten
is you can specify for your background task to be hosted in the foreground
process so both sit in the same process in that case and the advantage of that is if you
want to do interprocess communication between the foreground in the background well,
it's not interprocess communication that point it's just communication between those two
...to modules?
...much simpler if the average communication that you want to
...your background task in your foreground this can be useful again,
for those kind of more long-running tasks where you might have so you might have them running the same time
...your foreground the disadvantage of courses now you have to keep your whole for application around
in memory and especially on devices with limit amount of memory that
it very much increases the chance of your of your application to
not stay resident...in this suspended state.
So, that's kind of the basics of the background execution model and,
the converges that we've made a windows ten for universal windows applications I want to sort of finish
off...talk about to triggers specifically that are new...windows ten but,
I want to show you a quick demo of for both of those so one of the application
trigger am ...what we call this the application trigger it's because it's triggered by your
application...being able to clever with
...name basically what happens in this case instead of waiting for like a timer to go off for wi-fi
...avail or whatever you actually explicitly fire it from your application?
So, this is really useful if
...app need to sink a bunch of data at the beginning like if you're thinking much
of contacts or data from like a news feed or something at the beginning and the user
may launcher app check something real quick and the navigate away previously
your app wouldn't have time to...to...data application trigger allows you to do that and of
...more efficient than using something like extended execution because if you host
...a separate process
you're only using that small amount of memory and you're much more likely to be able to keep running for much longer.
I'll show you a quick demo of that.
So, the registration of this is almost exactly the same as before for the basic background tasks
so here and requesting access they think so on difference here I'm creating and application trigger.
And, after...register it I do two things one is I create a value
...this is the this is basically dictionary that I pass that I
...to the background task the...has information to know...
what is supposed to do there's a very simple lightweight way of passing information between your foreground your background.
So, I'll just put a couple strings and...anything that serialized able in this theological to
string into this value set and, then here's where the magic happens here I'm a
trigger I actually call request on it so,
this asks the trigger to fire right away.
And, I can get ... different results either was allowed
it was already running or for or for whatever reason it's been disabled from
running so-if users disable your background tasks.
...was allowed I'm showing you progress in the background
...I'll show you herewhat's happening in the background
task again very much exactly the same as the.
As any background task.
So, as soon as this app comes up the first pages
...kick-off this background pasta...thinking data in the background.
So, you can see register and then
my task immediately gets called to run I didn't have to do anything in this case...
explicitly called it from a foreground out so, you see hello here and,
it's going to start sinking data.
And, sending some...notifications hopefully there we go so those are
popping up like before but they're showing up at...action center here and,
if I kill this app my sinking still continues in the background there's thirty
percent there's forty percent so my background task right now is continuing to run in the background and,
...data even well my foreground app isn't running.
So, that's again particular useful for these kind of initial...operations is long-running...operations.
One other trigger I want to talk about is these socket trigger
is a really powerful new trigger that we've added in windows ten.
Which allowsallows app to have to have their network
connectivity maintained even when they're no longer running so, again,
if you're coming from windows store applications you may be familiar with the control channel trigger...a little bit little
bit more obscure this was basically trigger that would allow you to keep
a background task suspended memory sitting
on a network socket and, then waking that task up whenever there
was data coming in on that network socket the disadvantage that was a course your out how to stick around and memory so
didn't work very well on devices where there is a limited amount of memory so the big improvement with socket
trigger tasks is that we actually now broker that socket hold
onto it for-you in the operating system and that means you're tasking completely go away
completely be removed from memory and we will wake you up and reactivated whenever there's data on that so,
this is a good alternative to using w and asked if you have your own push notification system if you have
your own server infrastructure for sending push notifications half the room...
why whatever want to do that and the other half is like that sounds great I absolutely have that...want to do that but, yeah,
so, if you have that situation where you have your own sort of push notification
the system this is what this will be helpful there?
So, the way this kind of works is you create your socket in the foreground
...your background task and you hand-off your socket between the foreground in the background so,
if you're using your...in the foreground you grab socket from the socket broker
...do whatever you need to do and,
then and then you hand it back to the broker...your...goes away and they get reactivated if there's
...on that socket so I'll show you this quickly here in a demo.
So, I'm...to kick-off here really briefly I have a little,
little server program that just...little telnet server that runs
and, then a little bought that send messages to it so, these are just when thirty-two
...dot net applications consul applications and,
then here is the uw p application.
So, I'll just run through this.
So, again, here I'm registering the task.
Same as before same patterns before in this case I'm using a socket activity triggers
...this socket trigger.
And, if my socket trigger
is successfully registered then go and I connect my socket in
the background so here I'm just using a new stress
screen socket and connecting to local hosts that server that I showed you there a
little telnet server and on the socket on the stream socket itself there's this new
method called enable transfer ownership...id that I can make-up whatever
...and I say if I want to wake-up unconnected standby?
And, then and, then I say I'm done with it so I'm going to transfer ownership back to the
...broker with the name here and then this time
spanned here's how often I want the
...be...try and honor as...keep alive as possible.
So, here of connected and then what you'll see in a second is?
So, that...woke up and what's happening with the
...aziz sending a message every five seconds so,
what happened is I connected to that server?
And, then eye-hand the socket back to the broker and then my chart
...here then send a message
...and related back to my app.
Which then activated my background task so my app could have been completely
gone completely terminated not memory my background task would have been activated here in the run method?
So, in my run method by grab the trigger details which to which degree information about the socket and I can
retrieve the socket from there which is what I'm doing here I check the reason I say it was
because of socket activity which is great that means there's data on the socket that I want to process and,
then I read that data and, then.
So, I got a bunch of these...clear here.
But, again, my app could be completely gone and I would still get ...notifications
coming in and, my background task reactivated even when I'm not even when I'm not running anymore.
So, that's a very powerful new trigger for.
For network based applications the...listen to data coming in the background.
So, that's kind of main stuff I want to show you today just to wrap things up,
... great news for everything is the application life-cycle backer execution
is completely converge across windows across all the windows ten skews for universal
windows apps so what that means is that you can write the same code and
haven't run on all windows devices the thing of course you have to be aware
of is that despite all the new things you can do all the tonnes a new triggers in capabilities that we've
added resource are still limited on especially on our mobile devices and the
...devices so you have to be aware of what happens when there's
low memory or when the devices on battery and we need to...conserve resources in that case
so that's when you get these notifications from windows...about what your app is doing?
So, there's a few other sessions that you really should go
to so there's a couple sessions session on thursday that
we'll talk a lot about some of those new contacts and appointments triggers.
...session on friday around the new bluetooth triggers and,
then sort of I talked a lot here about how windows talks to
...app robert has a session on friday around what your app should do in those cases and how
should handle ...those kind of...a winning events so on internally the
new toast notification triggers will be covered in a session on friday
...thomas and then app services which is a great new feature?
That you probably are a lot about andrew session a rude has a has a session
...sandeep have a session on that.
On friday so, if there's any questions.
You have to
...now you really insiders lounge or you can reach out to me on twitter...hammering.
And, one more chance to evaluate the session.
Great thanks everyone.